Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, we are starting on חולין chullin. *Chullin*,
ב עמוד א *Beis Amud Alef*, and as I mentioned yesterday, this
מסכת masechet *Masechet* is actually traditionally called שחיטת חולין chullin. *Shechitas Chullin*
in contrast to זבחים Zevachim. *Zvachim* which is שחיטת קדשים kodashim, *Shechitas
Kodshim*, although it's not just about שחיטה shechita *Shechita* and as I
mentioned yesterday when we did an overview, it's extremely well-organized. It speaks
about all the steps that come about in terms of eating meat
that is not a קרבן korban *Korban*, speaks first about שחיטה shechita
*Shechita*, two פרקים *Perakim* about that, then about the טריפות *Treifos*, checking
for punctures in the wounds, then it talks about the מצוות mitzvot,
*Mitzvos* relating to covering the blood, which by the way is not
done by cows, covering the blood is only done by birds and
by חיות *Chayos* like deer and so on. The basic rule is
that you only cover you don't cover the blood of animals whose
blood normally goes on the מזבח *Mizbeach*. So בהמות *Behemos*, the blood
normally goes on the מזבח *Mizbeach*, so you don't cover the blood.
It's a little ironic, you only cover the blood of bird and
of חיות *Chayos* of like wild animals which blood does not normally
go on מזבח *Mizbeach*. Anyway, not slaughtering it and its mother on
the same day, and then talks about removing things like the blood
and the גיד הנשה *Gid HaNasheh* and the fat, and then not
cooking it with meat and milk, so all the various steps in
terms of what you have to do in order to eat meat.
So we start with our פרק *Perek*, which is שחיטה shechitah *Shechita*.
הכל שוחטין hakol shochtin *Hakol Shochtin*, anybody can shecht, ושחיטתן כשרה ushchitasan
kesheira, *VeShechitasan Kesheira* and when they shecht, the שחיטה shechitah, *Shechita* is
valid, חוץ chutz, *Chutz* with the following exception: חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan, *Cheresh Shoteh VeKatan*. A חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan
*Cheresh Shoteh VeKatan*, the normal triad of people who we normally assume
halachically do not have דעת *Da'as*, do not have intellect, חרש cheresh
*Cheresh* halachically halachic intellect, right, which means that halachically they cannot effect
halachically significant acts. חרש cheresh *Cheresh* is a deaf-mute, שוטה *Shoteh* is
somebody who is like insane, not really not aware of his surroundings
or what the significance of action, some technical discussions follow this in
חגיגה *Hagigah*, and קטן *Katan* is a minor, a boy under thirteen
or a girl under twelve. Now normally those are excluded from things
which require them to do not a physical act but an act
that requires that requires sort of defining what they are doing, like
for example they cannot enter into a transaction, a business transaction, because
it's not just a business transaction is not just affected by the
physical exchange of objects, it's by the intent and the knowledge about
what is the significance of what you are doing, you're buying something,
you're selling something and so on. So that would be like a
classic example of what they cannot do. A physical act maybe they
can do, so why can't they do שחיטה shechitah *Shechita*? So interestingly
the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* spells out why they can't do it, it
is not a categorical exception. The משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says שמא יקלקלו
את שחיטתן *Shema Yekalkelu Es Shechitasan*, the problem is that they might
actually mess it up because they are not fully either of full
דעת *Da'as*, a full intellect, a mature intellect, or fully aware of
their surroundings, and we're afraid that they actually just won't do the
act correctly. So it's a concern about the technical performance, it's not
a categorical exception. And because... what?
Why would a חרש cheresh.
*Cheresh* not be able to...? We assumed at the time, especially when
they didn't have means of communicating with a חרש cheresh *Cheresh*, that
that person wound up very much being outside of the normal realms
of society, wasn't able to receive information or communicate... what? It doesn't
mean
it doesn't mean that his muscles are his sort of muscle reflexes
are not good, it means his ability to understand what he has
to do and to and to sort of be pay attention to
what he's doing, that was the concern, but it is not a
categorical exception. Normally you say these persons are not considered to halachically
have דעת *Da'as* and cannot effect a halachic act. Here it was
just a question about their technical ability to do it correctly and
therefore the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* ends by saying וכולן ששחטו v'chullan she'shachatu,
ואחרים רואים אותם *VeChulan Sheshachtu VeAcherim Ro'im Osam* and if anybody slaughters
meaning even these three and they're being observed שחיטתן כשרה shechitatan kesherah,
*Shechitasan Kesheira* then it's valid because they're not really categorically excluded, it
was just a question about whether they technically performed it correctly and
therefore if it was being observed and somebody saw that they technically
performed it correctly, it was valid. So this is interesting because this
actually explores as I said the idea that חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan. *Cheresh Shoteh VeKatan* from some הלכות *Halachos* are completely categorically
excluded. I mean just think about a מצווה mitzvah *Mitzvah* for example,
you can't have a
minor satisfy do a מצווה mitzvah *Mitzvah* for you. Or you can't
have a minor do an act of a transaction, a sale, even
if somebody was observing and say oh no it was very clear
he knew what he was doing and he did all the technicalities
correct, those types of things are a categorical exception because it's not
fundamentally there about the physical act. Whereas this which is seems to
be fundamentally about doing the physical act correctly, the only problem is
whether they will do it correctly is whether they technically have performed
it or not and therefore if it's observed it suffices. So when
we get to that in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* we will see
about that and we will see again and we will have an
opportunity to explore the different ways in which חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan, *Cheresh Shoteh VeKatan* might be fully excluded or only a
concern about the actual performance. Question? Yes.
Why isn't a גוי *Goy* excluded?
That is coming up in the
next. The next series of people will have to do somebody for
example who is a non-Jew or somebody who is an apostate Jew.
And those types of people, those are more likely to be categorical
exclusions not just technical problems of performance and there אחרי עומדים על
גביו would not work if they are categorically excluded. So that's another
set of people we'll be seeing. Yes Rachel.
Isn't it also that a חרש cheresh is now not what we
thought it was?
Right. So there is contemporary literature about a חרש cheresh. nowadays
that would not fall into the category of חרש. cheresh One way
in which that's addressed is חרש שיכול לדבר מתוך הכתב cheresh sheyachol
ledaber mitoch haktav that a חרש cheresh who can communicate non-verbally but
through other means through writing. No, it's more in the, a little
bit in the ראשונים, rishonim, it's more in contemporary פוסקים. poskim. That
and so meaning there are two ways to go about a question
like that. One is you could say well the reason that he
was excluded doesn't apply nowadays. That's often a little bit trickier because
you know הלכה halacha often very much focuses on the quantified sort
of parameters not the reasons which would make it almost like too
free to redefine everything. So the way it's normally articulated therefore is
well the problem with the חרש is he was not communicate, you
know, he was said that he couldn't speak. Well nowadays he does
speak. He speaks through gestures and he speaks through writing so maybe
he would not be considered to be unable to speak. So that
is a whole, yeah, there are definitely contemporary תשובות tshuvot about a
חרש. Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara.
Can't you imagine that there weren't, it wasn't common to have in
those times a person of a חרש like gesture, gesture could demonstrate,
tell us, could learn, could communicate?
Well gesture, yes. How much could you communicate with any degree of
precision when you did not have a language, a sign language?
I mean, you know, what would be, what would be the signs?
And what about writing?
I mean, what about if somebody became חרש later in life and
was still able to write?
Yeah or actually learned. Yeah, I don't know if there's any history
about how much they were able to learn. I mean look, I
mean, I don't know.
I always understood that it was associated with other developmental issues.
Oh you mean because the assumption that he's a deaf mute means
that there's something else that's wrong and they're...
Well it's often actually associated with that, correct me if I'm wrong,
those who know better. But it's often associated with that.
Okay so I'll have to look into some of that discussion. I
mean there's a whole, there is a whole literature about that. Let's
hold that until we get to it in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara הכל שוחטין לכתחילה.
hakol shochtin l'chatchila. So it says anybody can slaughter. That means that
לכתחילה l'chatchila anybody can do it. And then the end of the
משנה Mishnah, says, the next line actually says, ושחיטתן כשרה בדיעבד. ushchitatam
keshera b'diavad. Their שחיטה shechita is valid, which means that there was
a, it was somewhat problematic but if they did it, it's okay.
So the גמרא's Gemara bothered that the first half sounds like לכתחילה
l'chatchila anybody can do it and the second half sounds like no,
there are some people that maybe לכתחילה l'chatchila shouldn't but בדיעבד b'diavad
is okay.
So we haven't even said who those people might be that might
be problematic but that at least is questioned. So אמר ליה רב
אחא בריה דרב לרב אשי. amar lei Rav Acha brei deRav leRav
Ashi. Rav Acha brei deRav said to Rav Ashi, וכל הכל לכתחילה
הוא? vechol hakol l'chatchila hu? Is every time it says הכל hakol
implies that לכתחילה? l'chatchila? No, sometimes it means everybody is valid to
do it but doesn't mean, doesn't mean like לכתחילה l'chatchila unpro, that
you know can do it without any problem, can do it right
at the outset. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, now we're going to go
through a whole list of הכל hakols to see whether it means
לכתחילה בדיעבד. l'chatchila b'diavad. The גמרא Gemara sometimes does this when in
the beginning of a מסכת it opens up with הכל. hakol. It
wants to under, it sort of talks about, brings in a lot
of different הכל hakols because it's a standard line in משניות mishnayot
to talk about the scope. Now another place where it does this
which is per, which is perhaps even more interesting
is in ערכין Erchin where it says what does הכל hakol include.
So it says הכל, hakol, everybody can do X. So everybody means
some people you might have thought might not have been able to.
Who is the people you're trying to include by the phrase of
הכל? hakol?
So for example, that's where the famous, that's where the גמרא Gemara
comes where it says הכל קורין את המגילה. hakol korin et hamagila.
Everybody can read the מגילה megillah and it says well that's including
even women. Right so that gets to the issue about like women
reading the מגילה megillah for men and so on. So that's in
ערכין Erchin where it tries to understand what הכל hakol includes which
is the more obvious question. Who are you trying to include by
the word הכל hakol who I might not have assumed was included.
Here the גמרא Gemara takes a different tack. It looks at all
the הכל hakols but it's trying to figure out a different question.
Does that mean that they can do it לכתחילה? l'chatchila?
Or does that mean only בדיעבד? b'diavad? That whoever those people that
you might have thought might have been excluded, are we saying that
לכתחילה l'chatchila they can do it even at the outset or only
בדיעבד? b'diavad? And it says, so that's if first assumes that הכל
hakol suggests they can do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. But it's saying now
it's going to question.
There's no practical הלכה halacha difference for שחיטה shechita is there, if
you do it לכתחילה l'chatchila or בדיעבד? b'diavad?
Well should we hire you to do it if you're on the
בדיעבד b'diavad list?
But if you
did it, בדיעבד b'diavad is no different but there's a לכתחילה l'chatchila
difference. So the גמרא Gemara says וכל הכל לכתחילה הוא? vechol hakol
l'chatchila hu? Does every time it say הכל hakol means that לכתחילה
l'chatchila these, you know, everybody can do it? אלא מעתה, ela me'ata,
if that's true, here we have from תמורה, Temura, הכל ממירין. hakol
memirin. Everybody can do תמורה. temura. Right, תמורה temura is when you
try to transfer the קדושה kedusha from one קרבן korban, to another
and the תורה Torah says you're not allowed to. But if you
try to do it, both animals are קדוש. kadosh. So it says
everybody can affect תמורה, temurah, אחד האנשים ואחד הנשים, echad ha'anashim ve'echad
hanashim, whether men whether women. So הכי נמי דלכתחילה הוא? hachi nami
delechatchila hu? Should I read that to mean that everybody is allowed
to do תמורה? temurah? It’s a biblical violation! והכתיב, Vehachtiv, the verse
says לא יחליפנו, lo yachlifenu, do not exchange, ולא ימיר אותו, velo
yamir oto, do not transfer it, טוב ברע או רע בטוב, tov
bera o ra betov, bad with good or good with bad. So
obviously הכל hakol doesn’t mean everybody is allowed to; it means that
if you do it, it’s effective. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
התם כדיקתני טעמא, hatam kidekatani ta'ama, there the משנה Mishnah explicitly spells
out that it does not mean לכתחילה. lechatchila. Because what does the
end of the משנה Mishnah say? It
says לא שאדם רשאי להמיר, lo she'adam rashai lehamir, this is the
end of the משנה, Mishnah not that a person is allowed to
do תמורה, temurah, אלא שאם המיר מומר, ela she'im hemir mumar, but
if he did תמורה, temurah, if he did it, then the תמורה
temurah was effective. The other animal also became sanctified. The sanctity didn’t
leave the original animal, but the other animal became sanctified. And then
the end of the משנה mishna says וסופג את הארבעים, vesofeg et
ha'arbaim, and you—this is an interesting phrase for getting lashes—you absorb the
forty. Okay, you receive the forty lashes. So you get the punishment
of the lashes. So it says yes, הכל hakol normally means לכתחילה,
lechatchila, which is why in that משנה mishna where it talks about
תמורה, temurah, it had to say explicitly, don't think we mean you
can do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, what we mean is is that תמורה
temurah is effective, but you’re still prohibited to do it, and if
you did it, you get lashes. So again, if anything, that’s a
greater evidence that the word הכל hakol does mean לכתחילה lechatchila because
that משנה mishna had to then spell out that this was an
exception to that; this does not mean לכתחילה. lechatchila. Here when we
say everybody does תמורה, temurah, it means it’s effective if everybody does
תמורה, temurah, but not that it’s allowed. Okay, so we're still arguing
that הכל hakol means that לכתחילה lechatchila it is allowed. But the
גמרא Gemara continues to challenge this. אלא, Ela, if that’s true, let’s
look in the beginning of ערכין: Erchin: הכל מעריכין, hakol maarichin, everybody
can make an ערך, erech, ונערכין, vene'erachin, and be נערך. ne'erach. Now
what does ערך erech mean? This was actually at the end of
ויקרא. Vayikra. There are two ways in which somebody can donate the
value of a person, including him or herself, to the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. One is if you say, "I vow upon myself, I
take upon myself to give the value of that person to the
בית המקדש." Beis Hamikdash. You say, דמי פלוני עלי, dmei ploni alai,
the value of that person on me. Now then, how would you
determine the value? You would determine the value of what would the
value of that person be—the only way you can determine a value
of a person is to say, well, what would it mean if
that person was made into an object of sale, meaning if that
person was a slave? How much would they go sell for? And
then you have to give that amount to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. That's if you say the value, דמי פלוני עלי. dmei ploni
alai. If you say, however, ערך, erech, which actually also means value,
but it’s a technical term. So there it’s where the גמרא Gemara
at the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, ספר ויקרא, Sefer Vayikra, spells out
that it’s determined based on a list. If it's male, it's this
much; female, this much. If it's between one month and between one
month and I think five years, it's a certain amount; between this
many years and that many years, it's another amount. There's a standard
list of what the ערך, erech, the sort of fixed value, is.
So again, ערך erech also means value, but it's a technical term
which means you determine the value based on the list that the
תורה Torah gives you, the chart the תורה Torah gives you. So
הכל מעריכין, hakol maarichin, everybody can do this act of vowing to
make an ערך, erech, to give a value, and that word הכל
hakol is coming to include—what does that include?
So even a minor—normally a minor cannot do, as we said, an
act of halakhic significance, but when it comes to vows, there’s a
category called מופלא סמוך לאיש, mufla samuch le'ish, a minor that is
within a year of being an adult, whether a boy or a
girl, and if they understand the significance of their vows, their vows
are binding. So therefore the word הכל hakol there is coming to
include a minor. So everybody can be מעריך, maarich, can take a
vow to obligate themselves in the ערך, erech, ונערכין, vene'erachin, can be
the object of an ערך. erech. Okay, so therefore—and what that means
is that if I say the value—the ערך erech of that person
on me is to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, even if, and
here's what the word הכל hakol includes, even if, for example, that
person was terminal or a person was unable to do any useful
labor and therefore had no market value, even though he has no
market value, you still—if you use the word ערך, erech, you go
by the standard—the list that the תורה Torah provides and the ערך—you
erech still give the ערך. erech. So everybody can be מעריך maarich
and can be נערך, ne'erach, can be the object of an ערך.
erech. נודרים ונידרים, nodrim venidrim, can make a
vow—and here the vow is to give the value, meaning the market
value, not the list of the תורה. Torah. So everybody can make
that נדר, neder, ונידרים, venidrim,
and also can be the object of that. And here the idea
of being the object of that would be the flip of the
other example I gave you. The תורה Torah says when it comes
to that standard list, it only starts from one month old up.
Let's say you said the ערך erech of that baby who was
just born is on me; you don't pay anything because anything under
then a month is not on the list. But if you say
not the ערך erech but the value of that baby is on
me, then you go by the market value and that could have
a market value. So that's included by the word נידרים, nidrim, can
be the object of a vow. Okay, so anybody can make these
vows and be the object of these vows in terms of valuation.
So הכי נמי, hachi nami, so that's the point of that משנה
ערכין. Mishnah Erchin. So the גמרא gemara says... הכי נמי דלכתחילה? Hachi
nami dilichatchila? Would you say that they're also לכתחילה lichatchila you're allowed
to make such vows? וכתיב v'chasiv that it says in the פסוק
pasuk וכי תחדל לנדור לא יהיה בך חטא, vechi techdal lindor lo
yihiyeh becha chet, but if you cease to make vows there will
be no sin. So it means you should not be making vows.
וכתיב v'chasiv and we have the famous פסוק pasuk in קהלת Kohelet
that says טוב אשר לא תדור משתדור ולא תשלם. tov asher lo
tiddor mishetiddor velo tishalem.
Better not to vow than to vow and not to satisfy them,
not to pay them. Of course, which leaves open the question which
is debated about רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir.
Okay, obviously it's not good to make a vow and not to
keep it. But what if you're going to make a vow and
keep it? Is that better than not making a vow at all?
So that is debated. ותניא, v'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braisa,
טוב מזה ומזה שאינו נודר כל עיקר, tov mizeh umizeh she'eino noder
kol ikar,
not vowing at all is even better than vowing and satisfying your
vow. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rebbe Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir says. Yes, for sure, you want to give something, give something,
but don't start it with a process of making vows because then
you're just asking for trouble. And even if in the end you
satisfied your vow, you know, you should not be asking for trouble.
So just give your money, give what you want to give, but
don't give it through a vow. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda אומר omer
no, טוב מזה ומזה נודר ומשלם. tov mizeh umizeh noder umishalem. The
best of is obviously not to make a vow and not do
it, but the best is to make a vow and to do
it. So actually he's okay with you making a vow as long
as you in the end end up doing it. So this is
a classic and famous debate between רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי
מאיר. Rebbe Meir. So now we have a problem. According to רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir, there is never a legitimate basis, there's never a
לכתחילה lichatchila for making a vow. So how could the משנה mishna
say everybody can make vows? Obviously it doesn't mean לכתחילה, lichatchila, you're
never supposed to make vows even if you're going to pay it.
So maybe it's going according to רבי יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda? So we
say it wouldn't even work according to רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. Why
not? ואפילו רבי יהודה לא קאמר אלא באומר הרי זה. v'afillu Rebbe
Yehuda lo ka'amar ella b'omer harei zeh. So even רבי יהודה, Rebbe
Yehuda, the גמרא Gemara is sort of choosing, it's not the simple
reading of רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, but it's choosing to read רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda in a very limited way. It's choosing to understand
that even רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda agrees that there's a problem if
you take a personal vow, that there's always a chance you might
not fulfill it. So we never want to say it's a good
thing to take a vow even if in the end you did
fulfill it because you've opened yourself to the risk, which is רבי
מאיר's Rebbe Meir's position. But so what do you do with רבי
יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda? So we say when רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says
it's okay to take a vow and to fulfill it, that he's
not talking about a personal vow, he's talking about when you actually
sanctify the object itself. Like you say, I'm donating this car to
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. I'm sanctifying this קרבן, korban, I'm donating
this pile of money to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. There, you
know, there's no personal obligation. So even if something happens to the
money, you know, it's not like you've not satisfied a personal obligation
because you've sanctified the money or the car, not taken a personal
obligation. So it's choosing to read רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda through the
lens of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and say that even רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda would agree you should never take a personal obligation. And
if that's true, we go back to the question of how did
the משנה mishna say everybody can take a vow, which suggests לכתחילה.
lichatchila. First Bobby and then
David, yes. It's alright, it's alright. I didn't get on any open
pages.
Yeah. Okay, go ahead Bobby, yeah.
So my question is why
is the, why vow anything? What's the purpose in vowing if it's
better not to vow and to do? It's almost like the highest
level of charity is to give anonymously.
Right, right.
So why, why does it observe certain
people?
Right, well you're asking psychologically or you're asking why the תורה Torah
even describes the category? I mean, the answer is somewhat the same,
that even if in some ideal way you should not be doing
this, some people, well you're thinking about like vowing in public like
a שול shul appeal that you want to take these, you know,
you want to do that, but I think we're talking about just
psychologically. You feel very religiously motivated at a certain moment and you
want to do something to express that, to say I'm going to
do this, I'm going to give this amount of money or whatever.
Right? So that's a way to express your religious motivation and your
religious desire, and it also might be a spur for you to,
you know, to do it. And if you don't make the vow,
maybe you're just saying, oh okay well I'm not supposed to make
a vow so I guess when I get back home I'll go
take out the money from the bank and I'll go deliver to
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Well then that's not going to happen.
So the way you sort of spur yourself to do it is
you take the vow. But then there's always the chance that you're
not going to fulfill it. An interesting thing to note alongside of
this, which I guess they don't teach too often in שולס, shuls,
is that you know the תורה Torah never speaks about a מצווה
mitzvah to donate money to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. I mean
it talks about the phenomenon of donating money to the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, it talks about making vows right in the end of
ויקרא, Vayikra, but it never says oh you have a מצווה mitzvah
to do it. The מצווה is more has to do with צדקה
tzedakah or giving money to the לויים Levi'im who work in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That could be analogous to paying the rabbis
their half salary. No, the half shekel went to the קרבנות. korbanos.
Right? But it never went to actually, so it's sort of like
the operating expenses. But you know other types of like capital donations
or whatever, you know, while that obviously was a major phenomenon that
went back to ancient times, we find these ancient synagogues that have
inscriptions about who donated them and gave money to them. But you
know, so it was obviously something that people were very motivated to
do, but there's actually not a מצווה anywhere in the תורה Torah
that when your שול shul is having a capital
campaign. Anyway, so a lot of that though, apparently, but that tapped
into a lot of people's religious motivations. So that very much appears
in the phenomenon of vows. But then, you know, and then the
גמרא Gemara here is starting to deal with that funny situation that
we might need vows to spur us to do it, and give
expression to that. But the גמרא Gemara is just concerned about the
negative possible consequence in terms of violation.
David, you had a question a few minutes ago. I had a
main question.
Yes. About the nature of the vow being the obligation. Right. You
want to say you'll give a hundred dollars in case of the
next five years.
So I don't think it has to be a negative connotation. Question:
You said that the individual doesn't do a vow, that they dedicate
the asset and that's not in the realm of personal responsibility.
Right. But if you control the asset, let's say I'm dedicating this
five hundred dollars to Beth Medrash, I'm going to deliver it next
time I'm in town. But then you use the money, you speculate
in the market, you lose the money. Right. Or if you're in
or you say I'm dedicating this cow and you don't pay attention
to your, in your pasture, and the cow gets lost. Right. How
is that not personal obligation?
Right. Well, first of all, in the case of the money, if
you say I actually am sanctifying this money, then you're not allowed
to start speculating and it's מעילה, meilah, you've misappropriated the funds. But
let's say, let's say in either case, I'm sanctifying this money or
this cow, and then you don't bring it in from the rain
or whatever, and you don't watch it and it gets lost. So
the point is that you don't have a personal obligation. If you,
however, if you have הקדש hekdesh funds in your control, you might
de facto become a type of a שומר. shomer. So if you're
negligent, you have to, you know, pay for your negligence because this
is הקדש hekdesh funds. But that would sort of cover cases of
negligence, but if there's cases that go beyond negligence, you don't have
a personal obligation to pay the money. It's just הקדש's hekdesh property
under your, you know, responsibility, under your control. De facto you might
be a שומר. shomer.
Yeah. Maybe you can speak more to לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד. bedieved.
If there are no practical implications.
Well, there are practical implications is that whether you should choose to
allow to give, if you should give your cow to be slaughtered
by somebody who לכתחילה lechatchila shouldn't do it.
What if they did?
So then that's... so again, the practical implications are at the לכתחילה
lechatchila stage. They're not practical at the בדיעבד bedieved stage, but there
are still practical implications. Don't give it. Here's somebody who's signing up
to be a שוחט shochet and say I'm sorry, you're on the
בדיעבד bedieved list. I'm going to first have somebody else be the
town שוחט shochet before you. It's a big practical implication to this
guy who wants to be a שוחט. shochet.
It almost feels like it's just a question of whether it's preferable.
I think that is, yes.
Because it doesn't feel like it. It feels like it has a
tougher legal status.
Yes. I mean, the word לכתחילה lechatchila is hard to translate into
English, which is why we usually use a Latin phrase, which is
ab initio. Ab initio you should not give it to certain people
and certain people should not do it ab initio at the outset.
If they did it, then it's okay. So it's not so, you
know, but at the outset, when I'm making the decision, should I
give it to you to שחט, shacht, the answer is I should
not. Not just it's not preferable for me to do it, I
should not at this moment in time. At a later moment in
time, if it's already done, then it's a different what?
Yes. But בדיעבד. bedieved.
בדיעבד bedieved is post facto.
Right. It would be nice if we had a word like pre-facto,
but we don't.
All right, let's go on. Okay. Yes.
This isn't usually the way we apply the idea of לכתחילה. lechatchila.
It's usually we apply it with some respect to the way the...
but this is, I mean, you don't have to do שחיטה shechita
either, right? So you can say לכתחילה... lechatchila...
Right. I mean, it's not like לכתחילה lechatchila of a מצוה, mitzvah,
but it is like לכתחילה lechatchila of, under these circumstances that you're
trying to שחט, shacht, who are the people that are preferable or
לכתחילה lechatchila should and who are the ones that should not. But
you're right, I mean, it's not sort of the sense of like
the, you know, by doing a מצוה.
mitzvah. I mean, a proof from a נזיר? nazir? Right. From a
נזיר. nazir. No.
But the real, I'll tell you, the real problem of this whole
analogy is, and maybe this is what you're saying, is that in
the case of the נדר neder or the תמורה, tmurah, the point
is, okay, you're trying to claim that לכתחילה lechatchila you shouldn't be
doing this activity, but once you're doing this activity, there's no difference
between the types of people we're talking about, right? Whereas here, what
we're trying to say is once you're doing the activity of שחיטה,
shechita, maybe there's a difference between the types of people. So saying
that there you shouldn't be doing the activity is not the same
as here where we're saying certain people should not לכתחילה lechatchila be
doing it. That is correct. Yes, so it's a weird גמרא Gemara
in that way. So let, and it's don't worry, it gets even
worse. So let's keep on going. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
okay, אבל אמר הרי עלי לא, aval amar harei alai lo, but
here we're saying רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree that you should
never take a personal, a personal vow. So the גמרא gemara says
וכל הכל לאו לכתחילה הוא, vechol hakol lav lechatchila hu, are you
trying to tell me that every time it says הכל hakol it
does not mean לכתחילה? lechatchila? Because you're trying to say that in
all these cases it meant that just בדיעבד bedieved you take these
vows? ואלא, ve-ela, here we have a couple of
משניות. mishnayot.
Let me know when they say הכל hakol is. What? Doesn't mean
everyone.
Doesn't mean women. Right, it doesn't mean everyone. Well, a lot of
these things end with, but a lot of these things, a lot
of these things fairly do end with the word חוץ, chutz. the
same way our משנה mishnah ended with חוץ.
chutz But the way that the sentence begins, with the word הכל
hakol at the beginning, tells you that there will be exceptions.
Right, that's a good way of putting it too. הכל hakol is
almost begging for the exception.
And yeah, these משניות mishnayot too have the חוץ chutz, in them.
So the גמרא gemara says, you said חוץ, chutz.
you said חוץ. chutz.
What? חוץ. chutz. Okay. חוץ. הכא נמי דלאו לכתחילה? hacha nami delav
lechatchila? So you mean to tell me that לכתחילה lechatchila these people
are not supposed to do it? So the גמרא gemara says, no,
חייבין לא קאמינא. chayavin lo ka'amina. No, no, no, when it says
everybody is obligated, obviously that means לכתחילה. lechatchila. But my question is
when it says everybody X, does it mean everybody לכתחילה lechatchila does
X, or everybody at least בדיעבד bediavad it works? So אלא מעתה,
ela me'ata, the גמרא gemara says, okay, I'll give you another example.
הכל סומכין, hakol somchin, everybody can do סמיכה, smicha, אחד הנשים ואחד
האנשים, echad hanashim ve'echad ha'anashim, whether men or women. So it doesn't
say the word חייבין, chayavin, but it's talking about סמיכה smicha and
clearly סמיכה smicha is an obligation. So הכא נמי דלאו לכתחילה? hacha
nami delav lechatchila? Would you say that that's not לכתחילה? lechatchila? והכתיב,
vehaktiv, the verse says, וסמך ידו ונרצה, vesamach yado venirtzah, that you
should do סמיכה smicha and it will be desired for you. So
you see that הכל hakol can clearly sometimes mean לכתחילה. lechatchila. So
the גמרא gemara says it, you know what? You're right. איכא הכל
לכתחילה, ika hakol lechatchila, sometimes הכל hakol means לכתחילה, lechatchila, ואיכא הכל
בדיעבד, ve'ika hakol bediavad, sometimes you have it. And again, I repeat
the point Dov said which bothered me as well, that here the
לכתחילה בדיעבד lechatchila bediavad is about whether the entire activity is something
that should or should not be done, whereas our question is, is
the group of people, are they all at the same level of
preferred list? But anyway, the גמרא gemara is not making that distinction.
So sometimes it means one, sometimes it means the other. אלא, ela,
but as long as sometimes it means בדיעבד, bediavad, your whole question
disappears. אלא הכל דהכא, ela hakol dehacha, here when it says all
shecht, ממאי דלכתחילה הוא דתקי לך? mimay de'lechatchila hu detikyulach? What made
you think that it meant everybody לכתחילה lechatchila can shecht, and then
you're bothered by the end of the משנה mishnah that says if
they shecht it's okay, which suggests only בדיעבד? bediavad? דילמא בדיעבד הוא?
dilma bediavad hu? Since הכל hakol can sometimes mean that בדיעבד bediavad
it's okay, so maybe the whole משנה mishnah means בדיעבד bediavad and
your whole problem goes away, which is the easiest thing to say.
Either don't get hung up, you know, don't get hung up on
it. Either ושחיטתן כשרה, kasher. which means it's okay בדיעבד, bediavad, is
a little לאו דוקא, lav davka, which is another possibility. Or הכל
שוחטין hakol shochtim doesn't mean that לכתחילה. lechatchila. It means if everybody
does it, it's valid, but not that everybody is preferable. Now before
we go on to see the answer, I do want to point
out something. It's too bad רבקה's Rivka not here because anytime סמיכה
smicha comes up relating to women, רבקה Rivka always
has something to contribute to the conversation. Here it says everybody can
do סמיכה smicha whether men or women. So if you take a
look here at this marginal note on the right hand, in the
brackets, the very far right hand margin. It says חיפשנו, chipasnu, do
you see in the brackets in the רש״י? Rashi? חיפשנו בכל המקומות,
chipasnu bechol hamakomot, we looked everywhere, ולא מצאנו כן בשום מקום בש״ס.
velo matzanu ken beshum makom bashas. We've never found anywhere in the
entire תלמוד Talmud this line that all can do סמיכה, smicha, men
or women. Because women are usually not included in סמיכה, smicha, they're
explicitly excluded. And it says ואדרבה, ve'adaraiba, the opposite is true. איפכא
מצאנו, ipecha matzanu, we found the opposite, that women are excluded from
סמיכה. smicha. ואפילו רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון ve'afillu Rabbi Yose veRabbi Shimon
that say they allowed women to do סמיכה, smicha, right, אינו אלא
רשות. einu ella reshus. They only said that it was permissible, but
not that they were at the same level of obligation as men.
So it's very—what? Who? I think that this is the person who
does the cross-references in the גמרא Gemara, itself, which is the, what's
his name, the who does the cross-references in? Yes, like the עין
משפט Ein Mishpat and the מסורת הש״ס, Masores Hashas, which is יהושע
יהושע בועז. Yehoshua Yehoshua Boaz. So anyway, but he's the person that's
put in all the
cross-references.
Permissible but not acceptable?
Yeah, but it wouldn't—that wouldn't fit in the word, the same type
of הכל hakol expression.
Where does it come from then? It's not... I don't know. It's
maybe... it could have been a תוספות. Tosafos. I have not checked
the, I have not checked other manuscripts. But it is fascinating that
here it has that phrase about women doing סמיכה, smicha, which is
to be found nowhere else. Yes.
What's so special about סמיכה smicha that women can do it?
Women can... well, you mean in this quote? The general assumption is
that women cannot.
Right? That's what the note was pointing out, that this line
quoted a source that said everybody does סמיכה, smicha, men and women,
but all other places in the תלמוד Talmud where סמיכה smicha is
discussed, it always says that women cannot do סמיכה. smicha.
But here it is an outlier.
Yes. Correct.
For the exact same סמיכה. smicha. Yes. So talks about סמיכה smicha
in other places?
Yes, and in every place it says הכל סומכין hakol somchin except
for women.
So it's a typo?
So that's the possibility. You have
to... I have to check the other manuscripts, which I haven't had
a chance to, to see if some don't have that phrase.
I also want to ask, is it about דבורה? Devorah?
דבורה... Devorah... oh, דבורה... Devorah... not my דבורה, Devorah, דבורה Devorah the
prophetess? Yes. No, we're not talking about the סמיכה smicha that we
use now to refer to rabbinic authority. We're talking about the hands
on the top of a קרבן, korban. a way of bringing
a
קרבן. korban, Allowed appears in another opinion
and contradicts other
places where it says a woman is everyone in all other places
it's assumed that women are not obligated and in most the possibilities
that women are
allowed. No, although there are times where it does happen that things
do get quoted differently in different גמרות. Gemarot. What? Apparently תוספות Tosafot
say הכל סומכין hakol somchim sounds like
בדיעבד. bedieved.
What? הכל סומכין Hakol somchim sounds like בדיעבד? bedieved? Why?
Hold on, let
me look for specific signs.
Why, Sally? It doesn't say הכל חייבים. hakol chayavim. Oh, it doesn't
say הכל חייבים. hakol chayavim. But the whole context of סומכין somchim
is so לכתחילה lechatchila context. It doesn't mean like... like it's בדיעבד.
bedieved. That's my point, yeah. It's a big point, yeah. Big things
happen.
I'm just going to check quickly, cause I
had intended to do it. Right? This is a דקדוקי סופרים. Dikdukei
Soferim. I mean, it's not as comprehensive as what we have now,
but
for the time it was totally comprehensive of all manuscripts. This is
some one of my classes and you never found a
problem.
Well,
somebody paid attention to the
problem.
That's very curious.
Yes it is, which is why I pointed it out.
I like that you do that.
Thank you. Ah, okay. So אחד הנשים ואחד אנשים echad hanashim ve'echad
anashim does not exist in some manuscripts.
Yeah, so basically there are manuscripts in which it does not exist.
So it could very well just be an error, a copyist error.
What? Yes, the asterisk is pointing you to the side note. Okay,
but it does not exist in some manuscripts. Okay, so let's go
on. So now the גמרא, Gemara okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
wants to say, so look, הכל hakol can mean בדיעבד, bedieved, so
the whole משנה mishnah. can be read as בדיעבד. bedieved. So what's
your problem? So אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said back, אלא
שחיטתן כשרה קשיא לי. ela shechitatan kesherah kashya li. I was bothered
by the phrase where the משנה mishnah says all can slaughter and
their שחיטה shechitah. is כשרה.
So that sounds like it's בדיעבד, bedieved, since it says שחיטתן כשרה,
shechitatan kesherah
which means after the fact we accept it, בדיעבד, bedieved, only post
facto, מכלל דהכל לכתחילה הוא. miklal de'hakol lechatchila hu.
So therefore, now this is exactly bizarre. He's like creating his own
problem. He says, if the second part means בדיעבד, bedieved, then the
הכל שוחטין hakol shochtim should be read to mean לכתחילה, lechatchila, not
בדיעבד. bedieved. Why? Why not make it consistent? דאי בדיעבד, de'ee bedieved,
because if הכל שוחטין hakol shochtim, means בדיעבד, bedieved, everybody can slaughter,
תרתי בדיעבד למה לי, tartei bedieved lamah li, why would I have
needed both phrases to say בדיעבד? bedieved? Just say one phrase, say
you know, שחיטתן הכל כשרה. shechitatan hakol kesherah. Since it says שחיטתן
כשרה shechitatan kesherah which means בדיעבד bedieved and you included this other
phrase of הכל שוחטין, Hakol shochtim, it sounds like you're trying to
say that it's something different, that it's לכתחילה. lechatchila. So this seems
like you're just asking to create a problem. I mean, you know,
if it weren't from the beginning too much of a manufactured problem,
here it really sounds like a manufactured problem. We accept that the
word הכל hakol can mean בדיעבד, bedieved, we accept that the second
phrase of the משנה mishnah. שחיטתן כשרה means בדיעבד, bedieved, but somehow
we're saying, oh, well once that means בדיעבד, bedieved, the first half
needs to mean לכתחילה lechatchila or else it's just repeating itself. And
if it means לכתחילה, lechatchila, now it's contradicting itself. So obviously it
would be better to repeat itself than contradict itself, but the גמרא
Gemara is choosing to have it read to contradict itself in order
to in the end be able to read more into the משנה.
mishnah. So the way to understand what's going on here, the only
way I can understand it, is that this is somewhat of a
manufactured problem. It's really no textual problem in the משנה mishnah. itself,
but the גמרא Gemara is looking for an opportunity to read more
issues into the משנה. mishnah And that's what we're going to have
now, ways of reading other details and other facts into the משנה.
Mishna, So let's take a look. Okay.
אמר רבה בר עולא. amar Rabbah bar Ula. So now we're going
to come up with the answers to this question, which is not
such a question. So says רבה בר עולא, Rabbah bar Ula, הכי
קתני, hachi katani, this is how to read the משנה. Mishna הכל
שוחטין, hakol shochtin everybody can slaughter, ואפילו ve'afilu and now we're going
to talk about who is included in the phrase of הכל. hakol.
Who might I have thought would have not been able to slaughter
that it has to tell me even this person can slaughter? So
who is that? ואפילו טמא בחולין, ve'afilu tamei bechullin, even someone who
is טמא tamei can slaughter חולין. chullin. Because that was only a
problem by קדשים, but it's not a problem by חולין.
chullin חולין על טהרת הקודש? Chullin al taharat hakodesh?
Well, we're going to see. So the גמרא Gemara says, טמא בחולין
מאי למימרא? tamei bechullin mai le'meimra? You don't need a משנה Mishna
to tell me that. Obviously a טמא tamei person can slaughter חולין.
chullin There's no issue of being impure when it's non-sanctified animals. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, בחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש. bechullin shena'asu
al taharat hakodesh. This is somebody that is... and there were these
groups of people after the time of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
that were very scrupulous about eating all of their food, even non-sanctified
food, with the same level of purity as it was in the
time of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And that, or so and
this existed even in the time of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
as well. Right? If anybody remembers from their reading of the Gospel,
you know
that Jesus is always eating with the prostitutes and the tax collectors
and there's a whole question about who are you eating with. And
that really... Is reflecting another phenomenon that we find in the גמרא
Gemara about the חברים Chaveirim that would only eat with people that
were of, like, a group of people, there was this group called
the חבר Chaver that was very scrupulous about keeping everything pure, not
just not just kosher but pure, and would always eat all their
food, even their non-sanctified food with purity. So this was a certain
practice that existed even in the time of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and continued afterwards. So let's say you're of those people, are
you allowed to שחט shecht your meat when you're impure, since you're
trying to eat your meat with a level of purity that is
normally reserved for sacrifices? So are you allowed to? So that's the...
Yeah, wouldn't if you...
If that's the way you live your life and that's the way
you eat, wouldn't you not... You would choose not to participate if
you were not pure, it doesn't make sense.
Right? Oh, you mean you would just...
Well, I mean you would automatically...
Okay, that's true, but let's say you're hungry and the only שוחט
shochet around is somebody that just became טמא tamei today, you know,
can you go ahead and do it if he's not going to
touch the meat, you know, can you allow yourself to do it
if there aren't other options? Okay, so וכסבר, v'kasavar, and it's of
the opinion, חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש כקודש דמו, chullin shena'asu al
taharas hakodesh k'kodesh damu, that if they're treated if... If you treat
your non-sanctified food with the purity of קודש, kodesh, then we give
them a status like that of קודש, kodesh, not really but like
that of קודש, kodesh, and you have to treat them in the
same way. So therefore, כיצד הוא עושה? keitzad hu oseh? So what
can you do if you're a טמא tamei person and you want
to eat your meat but you're eating your meat with the sanctity
of הקדש? hekdesh? So מביא סכין ארוכה ושוחט בה, mevi sakkin arucha
v'shocheit bah, you take a nice long knife that'll keep you distant
from the meat itself and you שחט shecht it, כדי שלא יגע
בבשר, k'dei shelo yigga babasar, in order so you should not touch
the meat. Now תוספות Tosafot has a whole question, even if you
touch the meat, meat only becomes impure, any food can only become
impure if it came into contact with a liquid after it... So
after fruit was picked or meat was שחט-ed, shecht where's the liquid?
And the blood is actually... The blood of שחיטה shechitah is... So...
So by הקדש, hekdesh, the blood of שחיטה does not... Does not
מכשיר. machshir. So תוספות Tosafot has a question, yeah, but it's חולין
על טהרת... chullin al taharas... But anyway, תוספות Tosafot has a question,
I'm just putting it out there, we're not going to fully explore
that. Anyway, so לכתחילה, lechatchila, so הכל שוחטין hakol shochtin, means
even if you're treating your meat with the purity of הקדש, hekdesh,
if you're טמא tamei you can still שחט shecht it as long
as you keep your distance and as long as you don't touch.
But ובמוקדשים לא ישחוט שמא יגע בבשר, uv'mukdashim lo yishchot shema yigga
babasar,
when it's real הקדש, hekdesh, a טמא tamei person should not שחט,
shecht, lest he touch the meat, ואם שחט, v'im shachat, but if
he שחט-ed, shecht ואומר v'omer and he says, ברי לי שלא נגעתי,
bari li shelo nagati, I am certain I didn't touch, then שחיטתו
כשירה, shechitatho kesheira, then it's כשר. kosher. So
by הקדש. hekdesh. So here's how we're reading the משנה, Mishna, right?
We are... Again, we're sort of forcing a complicated structure onto the
משנה Mishna. that is allowing us to read new cases. So the
read we're having in the משנה Mishna is הכל שוחטין, hakol shochtin
everybody can do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, ושחיטתם כשרה, u'shechitatam kesheira,
and בדיעבד bedi'avad it's okay. So that's setting us up to say,
here's a type of people that can do it לכתחילה lechatchila although
I might have not thought about that. A slightly different type of
people or different circumstances should not be done לכתחילה, lechatchila, but if
you went ahead and did it, then it'll be okay בדיעבד. bedi'avad.
So the first continuum we're doing is about being טמא. tamei. Everybody
can שחט shecht as long as it's חולין chullin even a טמא
tamei person, just be careful, even if it's... Even if it's חולין
chullin that's being treated like הקדש. hekdesh. That's the לכתחילה. lechatchila. But
who should not שחט? shecht? You shouldn't שחט shecht if you're טמא
tamei and it's real הקדש. hekdesh. But בדיעבד bedi'avad if you did,
שחיטתם כשרה u'shechitatam kesheira as long as you're sure you didn't touch.
So it allows us to set up this other series of like
לכתחילה lechatchila yes, this person not לכתחילה lechatchila but בדיעבד bedi'avad it
would be okay. All right? So that's the one way we're reading
it about being טמא. tamei. Now...
So now we continue reading the משנה, Mishnah חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן,
chutz me'cheresh shoteh v'katan, excluding the חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v'katan
דאפילו בחולין גרידי d'afilu be'chullin giridi even if it's pure חולין chullin,
and it's not about טומאה, tumah, בדיעבד נמי לא, bedi'avad nami lo,
even בדיעבד bedi'avad their שחיטה is not good, שמא ישהו, shema yishhu,
lest they mess it up. And here it spells out what mess
it up means. They pause during the שחיטה, שמא ידרסו shema yidresu
or they apply pressure, you're not supposed to apply pressure, שמא יחלידו,
shema yachlidu, which is like you uproot the סימנים, simanim, we'll talk
about all these. וכולן ששחטו, v'chullan she'shachatu, and if anybody did שחט
shecht and other people observed them, it's okay. So now we're coming
to explain the last phrase of the משנה. Mishnah. So presumably the
last phrase means even if the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan
שחט-ed, shecht if they were observed it's okay. But now the גמרא
Gemara is going to be bothered that then it should have said
ואם שחטו, v'im shachatu, if they שחט-ed shecht and they were observed.
Why does it say וכולן v'chullan, ששחטו, if anybody שחט-ed? shecht It
seems like it's a group even larger than the חרש שוטה וקטן.
cheresh shoteh v'katan אהי, Ahei, which group is this going on? אילימא
חרש שוטה וקטן, Ilima cheresh shoteh v'katan, if it's going on חרש
שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v'katan אהא קאי, aha kai, that was what
we were just talking about. ואם שחטו מיבעי ליה. v'im shachatu miba'ei
lei. It should have said, and חרש שוטה וקטן does it, it's
no good, but if they שחט-ed shecht and they were observed, it
is good. Why does it add the word וכולן, anybody who does
it? אלא אטמא בחולין, Ella atamei be'chullin, it's going on the case
of you were טמא tamei and if you were observed it's okay.
הא אמרת לכתחילה נמי שחט, Ha amrat lechatchila nami shachat, but you
said לכתחילה lechatchila that's okay. ואלא, V'ella, so what's left in the
משנה Mishnah that we said are the cases being referred to? אטמא
במוקדשים, Atamei be'mukdashim, somebody who is טמא tamei that שחט-s shecht a
קרבן, korban that there we say they should not do it. So
why do you need him to be observed for it to be
okay? בברי לי סגי, be'bari li sagi, we said that if he
And therefore if he was observed it's okay. So how are we
reading this משנה Mishnah, again? This is a, it's the question isn't
really a question, but it's an opportunity for the גמרא Gemara, to
read more issues into the משנה. Mishnah? So we're reading the משנה
Mishnah that says everybody לכתחילה, l'chatchila,
some people not לכתחילה l'chatchila but yes בדיעבד. b'diavad. So that now
we're focusing on the issue of being טמא. tamei. Everybody לכתחילה l'chatchila
even if you're טמא tamei and even if you're treating your חולין
chullin, like הקדש, hekdesh, it's okay, just keep away long knives, don't
touch it. But there is one person that should not do it
לכתחילה, l'chatchila, a טמא tamei person with sacrifices. And even that case,
בדיעבד b'diavad it's okay if they know that they didn't touch. חרש
שוטה וקטן not, and then the last thing is anybody who's observed
is okay, which refers not only to חרש שוטה וקטן but even
the טמא tamei person who שחט shacht a sacrifice. That if he
is observed, and even if he's not around to to report on
whether he's certain he didn't touch, we can trust the observation and
say he didn't touch. So we've introduced this whole new thing about
טומאה tumah here. Before we get on to the גמרא, Gemara, I
want to take a pause to mention two things. First of all,
the issue about טמא tamei שוחט shochet that he shouldn't שחט shacht
a קרבן korban lest he touch it. תוספות Tosafot asks a question:
It's very nice that he didn't touch it, but where exactly is
he standing?
A טמא tamei
person is not allowed to enter into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Okay, now, if he is טמא מת, tamei meis, he can go
according to דאורייתא d'oraysa he can go right up to the door
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and even be in the עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim if he's טמא מת tamei meis through מגע maga
with a body. He just can't be in the מקדש Mikdash proper.
So there you could imagine he's standing at the door of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash of the עזרת ישראל, Ezras Yisroel, the קרבן
is right inside and he's שוחט. shachting. The problem is that מדרבנן,
m'drabbanan, you know, they did not allow, and there's already an early
משניות, Mishnayos, a טמא tamei person to be anywhere in the עזרת
נשים. Ezras Nashim. עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim is 135 אמות amos long,
about 200 feet long. So תוספות Tosafot says it's a little hard
to imagine
that he has a knife that's 200 feet long. So תוספות Tosafot
says basically two answers. One is maybe we're talking about not in
the time the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash when they brought sacrifices on
the במות, bamos, because he can't imagine how you can get a
knife that long. And his other possibility is well, maybe it depends
where exactly you're standing. If you come through the front door you
can't be in the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, but maybe if you
sort of stand, you know, come through a different entrance, maybe it's
possible.
Anyway, תוספות Tosafot has a lot of problems with that. While we
are talking about the issue though about הכל שוחטין hakol shochtin. before
we get onto the next point of the גמרא, Gemara just to
take this breather, I want to point out one thing that I
forgot to mention in the משנה, Mishnah? that who is הכל, hakol,
who might הכל hakol be including? So if you take a look
back at the very first page, turn us back to the עמוד
א׳ amud aleph and look at תוספות Tosafot there, הכל שוחטין. hakol
shochtin תוספות Tosafot says the following. He says
כותב בהלכות ארץ ישראל. kosiv b'hilchos Eretz Yisrael. There was some גאוני
Geonic ספר sefer called הלכות ארץ ישראל Hilchos Eretz Yisrael which actually
had a lot of very bizarre rulings in it. And one of
the rulings in this book was דנשים לא ישחטו מפני שדעתן קלות.
d'nashim lo yishchatu mipnei she'daatan kalos. Women shouldn't שחט shacht because they
have, they're of light minded. They don't have the seriousness, the focus
to be able to do it correctly. ואין נראה, v'ein nireh, it's
not true, דאפילו במוקדשים שוחטות לכתחילה. d'afilu b'muktashim shochtos l'chatchila. Even by
קרבנות korbanos women can שחט shacht לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
And all the more so by non-קרבנות korbanos as כדאמרינן הכל שוחטין,
k'de'amrinan hakol shochtin, וכל הפסולים ששחטו בדיעבד וכו׳ v'chol hapsulin sheshachtu b'diavad
v'chu etc. etc. So הכל שוחטין hakol shochtin. for תוספות Tosafot clearly
includes women, and it's not only by חולין, it's even by קרבנות
korbanos and they can totally do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. And actually from
what I understand, there are a few women nowadays that are interested
in learning הלכות שחיטה. Hilchos Shechitah. I think historically we do know
about one or two women who were שוחטות. shochtos. But there actually
although interestingly you have this bizarre statement, as far as the sources
are all very clear that the לכתחילה l'chatchila actually includes women as
well. So I just wanted to mention that point about, because that's
something that's certainly included in the הכל שוחטין. Only חרש שוטה וקטן
are excluded. Gender is not an issue. Let's now turn back to
the גמרא Gemara and just talk about, now that we're talking about
being טמא tamei and explore that for a few more minutes. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, back on the ב׳ עמוד ב׳.
beis amud beis. האי טמא במוקדשים מהכא נפקא? hai tamei b'mikdashim me'hacha
nafka? The idea that a טמא tamei person should not שחט shacht
קרבנות, korbanos, you're telling me we learn it from here? That that's
included in this משנה? Mishnah. מהתם נפקא, me'hasam nafka, we learn it
over there in זבחים. Zevachim כל הפסולים ששחטו שחיטתן כשרה. kol hap'sulim
sheshachtu shechitasan kesherah. Any invalid person that שחט, shacht, meaning normally invalid
to do the עבודה, avodah, it is still valid to do a
שחיטה. Why? ששחיטה כשרה בזרים, she'shechitah kesherah b'zarim, and here's actually tying
into that תוספות Tosafot we just read, because
שחיטה can be done by non-כהנים, kohanim, בנשים binashim with women, ובעבדים
uv'avadim slaves, ובטמאים uv'tmeiyim and even טמא tamei persons. ואפילו בקדשי קדשים
v'afilu b'kodshei kodoshim and even with the most holy sacrifices. ובלבד שלא
יהיו טמאים נוגעים בבשר. uvilvad shelo yihyu tmeiyim nogim babasar. The only
issue is if you're טמא, tamei, don't touch the meat. So there's
an explicit משנה Mishnah, in זבחים Zevachim that tells you if you're
טמא tamei you can שחט shacht just don't touch the meat. So
why would it have to have been repeated implicitly in our משנה?
Of course it wasn't repeated at all, the גמרא Gemara is reading
it into our משנה. But okay, how can you read it into
our משנה, why is it necessary? So the So the גמרא Gemara
says הכא עיקר. Hacha ikar. No, here's the real teaching of that,
which is again bizarre because it's not even stated. התם Hasam over
there, איידי דתנא aidi de-tana שאר פסולין, shear psulin, since it's talking
about other invalid people like non-כהנים, Kohanim,
תנא נמי טמא במוקדשין, tana nami tamei be-mukdashin, it also gives the
case of the טמא. tamei. ואיבעית אימא, V-iba'is eima, another answer, which
is clearly the better one, התם עיקר. hasam ikar. There, in זבחים
Zevachim. is where it's really telling you the law that a טמא
tamei person, you know, לכתחילה lichatchilah shouldn't do it, בדיעבד bediavad he
can as long as he didn't touch the meat. דבקדשים קאי, De-be-kodshim
kai, because it's talking about קורבנות, korbanot, so there it's telling you
the primary
teaching. הכא Hacha here, איידי דתנא טמא בחולין, aidi de-tana tamei be-chullin,
since we're referring to a case of a טמא tamei person שוחט-ing
shecht חולין, תני נמי, tani nami, we're implicitly also referring to a
case of טמא במוקדשין, tamei be-mukdashin, a טמא tamei person שוחט-ing shecht
sacrifices. Again, we are, it's quite a fascinating גמרא Gemara that we're
having a whole discussion why teach this here if actually nothing was
said here. All that was said here is הכל שוחטין ושחיטתן כשרה,
Hakol shohtin u-shehitatan kesherah, but we are reading into these two innocent
four innocent little words an entire discussion about טמא tamei people שוחט-ing
shecht and not שוחט-ing shecht and so on and then figuring out
why does it have to be repeated. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is
going to continue with this to use this as an opportunity to
read in other people who may or may not שוחט shecht לכתחילה.
lichatchilah. Before we end, I just wanted to mention about the issue
about making vows because I know that and you know donating things,
a very interesting רמב"ן Ramban on this point, that the רמב"ן Ramban
says the following things because he's also bothered with this whole idea
of should you really not be taking vows and don't we know
that people in the תורה Torah take vows and יעקב Yaakov takes
a vow, וידור יעקב נדר לאמור. Vayidor Yaakov neder leimor. So he
says the following thing which I thought was quite fascinating. I'll just
read it quickly. He says
ועוד היא דכתיב וידור
יעקב, Ve-od hi di-chsiv Vayidor Yaakov, יעקב Yaakov made a vow, וכתיב
וידר ישראל, u-chsiv Vayidor Yisrael, וכתיב נדרו ושלמו לה' אלהיכם כל סביביו.
u-chsiv Nidru ve-shalmu la-Hashem Elokeichem kol sevivaiv.
ותירצו, V-tirzu, so one answer is דבשעת צרה שאני, de-be-shaat tsarah shani,
which is quite fascinating because this fits into other positions of the
רמב"ן. Ramban. When people are in times of great trouble, then there's
particularly an allowance to make a vow, to make like this religious
commitment. By the way, the רמב"ן Ramban says there's no daily מצוה
mitzvah to pray, but there is a מצוה mitzvah to pray when
you're at a time of trouble and a time of distress. So
that's interesting. Okay and then he says ולי יראה שלא אסרו אלא
בקדשי מזבח שמא יבוא לידי תקלה ואין בקרבנות צורך גבוה כדכתיב הנה
שמוע מזבח טוב. Veli yeira-eh she-lo asru ela be-kodshei mizbeiah shema yavo
lidei takalah ve-ein be-korbanot tsorech gavoah ki-chsiv hinei shemoa mi-zevach tov.
He says to me it seems that the problem with vowing is
number one, you might not fulfill it and number two, you know,
you're not really serving any larger purpose, God doesn't really need your
קורבנות. korbanot. Like we said at the end of the גמרא yesterday,
God says I don't need your קורבנות, korbanot, you're doing it for
yourself. So therefore you're only doing it for yourself and you might
come to sin, don't take vows about bringing קורבנות. korbanot. אבל לצדקה,
Aval litzdakah, if you're taking a vow for giving to charity, ולהפיש
איסר לעניים u-lehafish issar laniyim or to give money to the poor,
ואין צריך לומר לקיים, ve-ein tsorech lomar lekayem, it doesn't go without
saying to fulfill other מצוות, mitzvot, נשבעין ונודרין, nishba-in ve-nodrin,
then it's appropriate to make vows. So this is a fascinating רמב"ן,
Ramban, it's like again this critique about קורבנות korbanot are not so
important, which is an interesting way in a way almost that we
ended זבחים. Don't do it for me, I don't need your קורבנות,
korbanot, you need it and therefore there, because you might not fulfill
your vow, there's a particular problem. But vows that actually are, will
end in doing something good in the world, giving money to the
עניים, aniyim, doing מצוות, doing things that are really important to be
done, there it is appropriate to make vows. So David, now you
can once again, we can once again make the appeals for the
שול shul for their capital campaign. Yes.